Guide to the New York State College of Home Economics records, 1875-1979
College of Home Economics records, 1875-1979
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
New York State College of Home Economics records,
1875-1979
23-2-749
New York State College of Home Economics
ca. 79.7 cubic ft.
Correspondence, photographs, course materials, records, pamphlets, booklets, compact disks, videos, audio tapes, and ephemera.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Collection includes administrative records; records of the College's involvement with government, educational, and private organizations at the national, state, and local levels; College activities within divisions of the University; the College's involvement in World War I, World War II,; student activities of undergraduates, graduate students, and alumni; teaching and research studies and reports; and extension work. Also included is a large amount of material related to the history of the College of Home Economics, Martha Van Rensselaer, Flora Rose, and their correspondence previous to 1921.
ORGANIZATIONAL HISTORY
Home Economics began as part of the Extension Service in 1900 with the arrival of Martha Van Rensselaer and the establishment of the Farmers' Wives Reading Course. In 1903-1904 Martha Van Rensselaer and Anna Botsford Comstock taught three courses within the College of Agriculture at Cornell University, relating to home and family life. In 1907 the Department of Home Economics was established at Cornell, with Martha Van Rensselaer and Flora Rose as its first instructors. In 1911 the two women became the first full-time female faculty members at Cornell. The Department of Home Economics became a school in 1919 and in 1925, the first state chartered College of Home Economics in the country. In 1969 it was renamed the New York State College of Human Ecology.
CHRONOLOGY: COLLEGE OF HOME ECONOMICS
1900 Martha Van Rensselaer arrived at Cornell to organize a reading course for farmers' wives
1901 First bulletin of the Cornell Reading Course for Farmer's Wives, Saving Steps, published and distributed
1903 Three courses relating to home and family life offered for credit at Cornell University
1905 First winter course taught in home economics. The program was non-credit, open to any woman in the state, and it continued until 1921
1907 First curriculum for the four-year course in home economics completed
Flora Rose joined the staff of home economics
Department of Home Economics established
1909 Martha Van Rensselaer received her A.B. from Cornell University
1911 First three students graduated from the Department of Home Economics
Martha Van Rensselaer and Flora Rose granted the first full professorships for women at Cornell
1912 Martha Van Rensselaer and Flora Rose voted members of the Cornell faculty and named co-directors of the Department of Home Economics in the College of Agriculture
1913 Department of Home Economics moved into its own building, called Comstock Hall, today the Computing & Communications Center
1914 Smith-Lever Act passed by United States Congress
1919 Department of Home Economics became the School of Home Economics within the New York State College of Agriculture
1922 Department of Hotel Administration established in the School of Home Economics
First M.S. in Home Economics awarded to Amy L. Hunter
1923 Martha Van Rensselaer named one of the twelve greatest women in the country by the League of Women Voters
1925 New York State College of Home Economics established at Cornell
Purnell Act made federal research funding available through 1930
1930 First Ph.D. in Home Economics at Cornell University awarded to Helen Canon
1932 Martha Van Rensselaer died
1933 College of Home Economics moved into Martha Van Rensselaer Hall
1936 Flemmie Kittrell awarded a Ph.D. in Home Economics, the first African American in the United States to earn such a degree
1940 Flora Rose retired and Mary Henry appointed acting director of the College
1941 Sarah Blanding appointed director of the College
1942 Sarah Blanding became the first female dean at Cornell
1944 Van Rensselaer and Rose Lectures established to bring distinguished women, such as Margaret Mead, to campus
1946 Sarah Blanding resigned to become first female president of Vassar College
Elizabeth Vincent appointed dean of the College
Home Economics Education became a department in the College
1947 First television broadcast planned and produced by the College of Home Economics
Catherine Personius, Head of the Department of Food and Nutrition, appointed coordinator of research and assistant director of Cornell University Agricultural Experiment Station
1949 College of Home Economics became one of thirty-two constituent units of the State University of New York (SUNY)
1952 Mann Library opened, combining the libraries of the College of Agriculture and the College of Home Economics
1953 Elizabeth Vincent retired
Helen Canoyer became dean of the College
1954 The School of Hotel Administration separated from the College of Home Economics and became its own college, with H. B. Meek as dean
1955 Home Bureau Federation established
1958 Fifty-seven home economists from twenty countries gathered for the first time at the Institute and Workshop on International Education in Home Economics
1959 Flora Rose died
1960 Catherine Personius elected as the first female faculty trustee
1962 Television and Film Center completed
1963 Ghana Project established to assist women's education in Africa
1964 Home Economics International Activities Office established
1966 Head Start Program initiated
President's Committee to Study the College of Home Economics convened with Sara Blackwell as chair
1967 Final report of the President's Committee to Study the College of Home Economics submitted
1968 North Wing of Martha Van Rensselaer Hall dedicated
Dean Helen Canoyer retired
1969 David Knapp appointed dean
New York State College of Home Economics reorganized and renamed the New York State College of Human Ecology
CHRONOLOGY: MARTHA VAN RENSSELAER
June 21, 1864 Born in Randolph, New York
1884 Graduated from Chamberlain Institute, Randolph, New York
For 10 years taught in public schools of western New York
1894 Elected school commissioner of Cattaraugus County, New York and served for 6 years.
1896-1903 Lecturer in teacher's institutes and Secretary of the State Summer School at Chautauqua.
1900 Called to Cornell and started educational extension courses.
1907 Instructor in Home Economics at Cornell.
1909 A.B. degree from Cornell.
1911 Professor at Cornell.
1914-1916 President of the American Home Economics Association.
1917 During World War I made head of the food conservation work in New York State and was appointed to the office of director of the food conservation division of the U.S. Food Administration by Herbert Hoover.
1920 Appointed joint head of Home Economics at Cornell with Flora Rose.
1923 Sent to Belgium to study the educational needs of women for the Commission for Relief in Belgium.
1929 Appointed director of the White House Conference for Child Health and Protection by Herbert Hoover.
1930 Received honorary D.Ped. from the New Yokr City College of Teachers.
1932 Martha Van Rensselaer Hall built; Martha Van Rensselaer died in New York City May 26, 1932.
CHRONOLOGY: FLORA ROSE
October 13, 1874 Born in Denver, Colorado.
1932-1940 Instructor at Kansas State Agricultural College.
1904 B.S. from Kansas State Agricultural College.
1907-1911 Lecturer at Cornell in Home Economics.
1909 M.S. from Columbia University.
1911-1940 Professor and head of the Department of Home Economics at Cornell.
1917-1919 Director of food conservation program in New York
1923 Belgian study of nutrition of school children for the Educational Foundation of the Commission on Relief for Belgium.
1924 Member of Weight Control Conference called by New York Academy of Medicine and the American Medical Association.
1931 Ph.D. from Albany State Teachers College.
1932-1940 Director of the College of Home Economics.
1940 Retired from Cornell as Emeritus Director.
July 25, 1959 Died in LaJolla, California.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The collection includes administrative records that document the College's involvement with government, educational, and private organizations at the national, state, and local levels; the College's involvement in World War I, World War II, defense, and relief committees; student and alumni activities; teaching and research studies and reports; extension and outreach work; College committees and activities including the Farmers' Insitute, Farm and Home Week, Honors Day and Home Economics Institutes. The collection contains correspondence from Martha Van Rensselaer, Flora Rose, Liberty Hyde Bailey, Franklin and Eleanor Roosevelt, Carrie Chapman Catt, Susan B. Anthony and from alumni, until the 1960s. There are also blueprints, sketches, samples and photographs of Martha Van Rensselaer Hall and its construction; a large series of photographs, negatives, and slides depicting all aspects of the College, including Deans Sarah Blanding, Elizabeth Vincent, Helen Canoyer, and David Knapp. Also, letterbooks and genealogy of Martha Van Rensselaer; including photographs, slides, negatives, an audiocassette recording of Kathleen Babbitt on Martha Van Rensselaer, CD's containing the scanned photographs from box 39, videos of early historic films concerning home economics, a box of dinner plates belonging to Flora Rose,and the original Home Bureau Creed.
Also, the film, "History of the College of Home Economics," (16 mm. sound, black and white, 5 min.), ca. 1968; a Hugh Troy photograph of a Home Economics pageant on Cascadilla Field, 25 July 1924. Includes bound Faculty Meeting minutes (1925-1969), Department Head Meeting minutes (1944-1969) and a tea set used by the college.
New York State College of Home Economics.; Rose, Flora, 1874-; Van Rensselaer, Martha, 1864-1932.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Roosevelt, Eleanor, 1884-1962.; Blanding, Sarah Gibson, 1890-; Catt, Carrie Chapman, 1859-1947.; Canon, Helen, 1888-; Knapp, David C.; Vincent, Elizabeth Lee, 1897-; Bailey, L.H.q(Liberty Hyde), 1858-1954.; Anthony, Susan B.q(Susan Brownell), 1820-1906.; Cornell UniversityxStudents.; New York State College of Agriculture.; New York State College of Home EconomicsxAlumni and alumnae.; New York State College of Home EconomicsxHistory.; New York State College of Home EconomicsxStudents.; State University of New York.; New York State Emergency Food Commission.; Cornell UniversityxAlumni and alumnae.; Farmers' Institute (Cornell University); Farmers' Week (Cornell University); Babbitt, Kathleen.; Troy, Hugh.; New York State College of Human Ecology.; Home economics.; Home economics--Equipment and supplies.; Home economics--International cooperation.; Home economics--Study and teaching.; Home economics extension work.; Martha Van Rensselaer Hall (Cornell University); Women--Suffrage--United States--History--Sources.; Women reformers.; Women scientists.; Reconstruction (1914-1939); War relief.; Women--Education.; World War, 1914-1918--Belgium.; World War, 1939-1945--Civilian relief.; Genealogy--New York (State).; Women college teachers.; Architectural drawings.; Blueprints.; Negatives.; Videotapes.; Scrapbooks.; Sketches.; Slides (photographs).; Photographs.; Audiocassettes.; Motion pictures (visual works)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Boxes 60-63, 70-72, 75-76, and 83-84 are restricted to the permission of the office of origin.
See also New York State College of Human Ecology records, #23-2-2817.
See also Cornell University Cooperative Extension records, #21-24-1975.
See also 4-H Club records, #21-24-692.
Boxes 70, 71, 72, and 75 have been removed and transferred to collection #23-11-4061, New York State College of Human Ecology Alumni Affairs and Development Office records
RELATED MATERIAL
Additional material and digital versions can be found online here:http://ecommons.library.cornell.edu/handle/1813/22044
SERIES LIST
Series I. Administration and Personnel records, 1906-1977,
Boxes 1-10, 60-63, 78-82, 85-86
Administrative records are filed by council, committee, or department; personnel records are filed alphabetically within the category of their employment including academic staff, department staff, and graduate students.
Series II. Cooperation of the College with Governmental, Educational, and Private Organizations, 1916-1959.
Boxes 10-15
Records are filed by groups designated as either government related, educational institutions, or private organizations. Files are also broken down into national, state, or local designations.
Series III. All College Activities, 1909-1979
Boxes 15-17, 73, 76
Filed by topics including Cooperation with College of Agriculture; Divisions of the University; SUNY; and Farmers Institute and Farmers Week, and Home Economics/Human Ecology Alumni Institutes (1952-1979.)
Series IV. World War I, World War II, and Wartime, Defense, and Relief Work, 1917-1947.
Boxes 17-19
Includes material about the U.S. Food Administration, Thrift Program, food conservation effort, National Defense Program, New York State Emergency Food Commission, New York State War Council, and Flora Rose's work with Belgian War Relief.
Series V. Student Activities, ca.1918-1969.
Boxes 19-21, 51, 65, 74, 83
Includes material about undergraduate and graduate programs, homemaking apartments, summer sessions, winter courses, nursing, fellowships, scholarships, international students, student organizations, the graduate staff organization, and alumni studies and surveys.
Series VI. Teaching and Research Series, 1911-1967.
Boxes 21-23, 84, 87, 89
Includes studies and reports including state projects on child development and family relationships, home economics education, textiles and clothing, housing and design, institutional management, hotel administration, and miscellaneous projects and reports. Also includes a history of research and the college research committee.
Series VII. Extension Series, 1901-1948.
Boxes 24-25
Includes general information with an early history of extension, material about extension publications, and Farmers' Wives Reading Course and Clubs material and booklets, 1901-1940.
Series VIII. Correspondence
Boxes 25-26, 70-72, 75, 102
Between Martha Van Rensselaer and Flora Rose with Cornell staff including A. R. Mann, Liberty Hyde Bailey, W. A. Stocking, Cornelius Betten, Jacob G. Schurman; Extension staff including R. H. Wheeler and M. C. Burritt; with agriculture professors; with politicians including the Hoovers and Roosevelts; and invitations and calling cards.
Series IX. Furnishings, 1927-1954.
Boxes 27-32, 100
Includes blueprints, sketches, photographs, samples, specifications, orders, estimates, plans, inventories, and printed material about the building of Martha Van Rensselaer Hall and all of the College of Home Economics office spaces, departments,classroom facilities, practice apartments, and laboratories.
Series X. College History, 1875-1965.
Boxes 33-38, 52-54, 56-57
This series was artificially created and includes material taken from other series, it depicts a history of the college from several research points including the history of Martha Van Rensselaer's life, Flora Rose's life, a small amount of material about the deanship of Sarah G. Blanding; annua1 reports of the college; Belgian War Relief material collected by Flora Rosa; material about the College Bill which was a state bill to start the College of Home Economics; and includes correspondence, telegrams, clip pings, photographs, printed material, biographical sketches, reminiscences, minutes of meetings and committees, conference material, and interviews.
Series XI. Photographs, Negatives, Slides, Videos, Motion Pictures, ca.1900-1968.
Boxes 39-43, 49, 55, 64, 68, 77, 90,96, 100, 101, 106
With early photos and a tintype of Martha Van Rensselaer's family. Photographs are identified and described, most are dated. They are arranged by topics including resident teaching, public relations efforts, all-college activities, administration and personnel, departments and divisions, buildings and equipment, and history of the College.
Series XII. Printed Material, 1895-1970.
Boxes 44-47, 66, 67, 88, 98-99, 102, 103, 104
With reports, programs, announcements, schedules, calendars, pamphlets, booklets, and volumes concerning the College of Home Economics including programs of the Homemakers' Conference; programs of the Annual Convention of the Association of Land-Grant Colleges; Home Economics News; Belgian publications (in French); and Farmers Wives Reading Course Booklets, 1901 - 1940.
Series XIII. Scrapbooks and Miscellany, 1902-1962.
Boxes 40, 48-50, 58-59, 64, 91-95, 97, 105
Includes scrapbooks about the Farmers' Wives Reading Course, 1902-1912; Farm and Home Week Special, 1946; "Let's Make a Dress"; a letterbook with copies of Martha Van Rensselaer's letters,1902-1905; Dean Canoyer's desk calendars; and diplomas, a broadside, and an etching done by Anna Botsford Comstock.
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Administration and Personnel
  - Organizational structure of the College - change in organization from School to College (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Changes made in instructional & organizational policy (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Organizational charts of the College (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Policies, rules, and regulations, 1932-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Policies, rules, and regulations,1940-1946 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Salary policies in the New York State Colleges, Schools and Experiment Stations administered by Cornell (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - College Council (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - College Council-1920 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - College Council-1922-23 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - College Council-1929-1931 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - College Council-1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - College Council-1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - College Council-1941-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - College Council-1942-1943 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - College Council-1943-1944 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - College Council-1944-1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - College Council-1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - College Council Membership 1945-1953 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - College Council 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - College Council, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - College Council, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - College Council 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - College Council, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - College Council, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - College Council, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Committee on Higher Education for Women, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Plan Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Committee on Admissions, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Committee to Evaluate & integrate the Homemaking Core, 1947-1952 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Extension Educational Policy Committee, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Committee on Program for Extension Staff Members, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Committee on 5-year Teaching Program, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Graduate Staff Committee (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Educational Policies Committee (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Resident Educational Policy Committee 1922-1940 (Box 1, Folder 35-36)
  - Resident Educational Policy Committee 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 37-38)
  - Resident Educational Policy Committee 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - Resident Educational Policy Committee January 1952-July 1953 (Box 1, Folder 41-43)
  - Resident Educational Policy Committee September 1953-1954 (Box 1, Folder 44-45)
  - Resident Educational Policies Committee - 1946-1959 (Box 86, Folder 2)
  - Resident Educational Policies Committee - 1959-1969 (Box 86, Folder 3)
  - Honor Committees 1924-1932 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Library Committee 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Nominating Committee 1946-1954 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Publication Committee 1946 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Committee on Scholarship 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Committee for selection of students to attend Merrill Palmer School 1946 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Committee on selection of students for preparation for secondary school teaching 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Committee on selection of students for teacher training (proposed) 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Committee on selection of students for professional training in Food & Nutrition and Institutional Management 1946 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Social Committee College of Home Economics 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 55-56)
  - Committee on student petitions and academic standing 1946 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Working Rules Committee material 1946 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Committee on Working Rules-Minutes-1946 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Working Rules Committee 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Special Committee on Working Rules for the Faculty 1945-1960 (Box 1, Folder 61-63)
  - Appendix A 1946 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Appendix B 1946 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Appendix C 1946 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Departments, Divisions
    - Organization of Departments in the College 1920-1925 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Child Development & Family Relationships: History 1925-1930 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Child Development & Family Relationships Dept. 1925-1926 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Child Development & Family Relationships Dept. 1927-1929 (Box 2, Folder 5-9)
    - Child Development & Family Relationships Dept. 1930-1937 (Box 2, Folder 10-13)
    - Child Development & Family Relationships Dept. 1940-1951 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Child Development & Family Relationships Dept: Parental Education 1928-1931 (Box 2, Folder 15-17)
    - Child Development and Family Relationships Course: Nursery School 1925-1930 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
    - Child Development and Family Relationships Course - Nursery School 1923-1924 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
    - Laura Spellman Rockefeller Memorial for Child Training 1924-1925 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Laura Spellman Rockefeller Memorial for Child Training 1928-1929 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Nursery School Teacher Preparation Curriculum Second Report Committee-of-Six (Draft I) - tentative (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
    - Committee - Nursery School Teacher Curriculum 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Student Guidance (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Family Life 1937-1938 (Box 2, Folder 29-30)
    - Extension Teaching and information 1941-1947 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Extension Teaching and Information 1916-1928 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
    - Food and Nutrition Dept. 1927-1945 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
    - Economics of the Household & Household Management Dept. 1925-1939 (Box 2, Folder 36-37)
    - Economics of the Household with photographs of the Home Improvement Living Room (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Household Economics and Management: Early Development and History 1908-1929 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Dept. Household Economics and Management 1929 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Institutional Management: History 1920 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Housing and Design Dept. (household art) 1920-1944 (Box 2, Folder 42-44)
    - Institution Management Dept. 1919-1945 (Box 2, Folder 45-46)
    - Textiles and Clothing: History 1922 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Textiles and Clothing Dept. 1927-1943 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Other Divisions, Former Departments, etc
    - Home Economics Cafeteria: Correspondence and Advertising Matter on Food & Food Products to 1921 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Home Economics Cafeteria: equipment, correspondence, to 1921 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Home Economics Cafeteria: general operation, correspondence, to 1921 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Home Economics Cafeteria: staff, to 1921 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - SATC Mess Hall in Home Economics Cafeteria 1918-1919 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
    - Library and books: correspondence and advertising matter,includes correspondence from Institution of Nutrition, Manila, Philippines, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 7-8)
    - Department's laundry service 1919-1920 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - M.V.R. Hall Library and Library Handbook (Box 3, Folder 10)